Guide to the Michael L. Belangie Papers
Department of Special Collections
Belangie, Michael L. Papers,
1945-1980
M0924
Belangie, Michael L.
9 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Biography
Born in Butte Montana, on June 29, 1907, Michael Louis Belangie was the eldest of three children. His father was of French-Canadian origin, and spent his working life as a miner. The tall, thin, dark, and conservative, "Mike," as he came to be known, typified the "American Dream," rising from humble origins to success, comfort, and recognition in the community in which he chose to make his home, Menlo Park, California.
The young Belangie was a "go-getter" from the beginning. He graduated from Butte High School and went to work for the Montana Power Company as lineman, and later as hydroelectric station operator. Then he entered the University of Montana in Missoula. But after two years there, he left school. The Depression was sweeping the country. Belangie quickly landed a job as timekeeper and draughtsman for the U.S. Forest Service. This first taste of civil service started him on a career path that he followed for the rest of his life.
From 1939 to 1943, Belangie worked for the U.S. Department of Agriculture, reaching the position of Regional Field Supervisor, working in the San Francisco office. His work lasted throughout the early critical years of World War II, when food rationing became a reality in the United States.
Belangie volunteered for the U.S. Army in l943, and was assigned to the 115th Combat Engineers Battalion in the Pacific Theatre, seeing duty in the Philippines, New Guinea, New Britain, and the Admiralty Islands. As a tech sergeant, he helped to establish and administer Engineer Supply Depots, and supervised operation of supply lines to elements of the 40th Infantry Division in forward areas. He was awarded the Bronze Star for his Army service.
Discharged from the Army in 1945, Belangie joined his wife of ten years, Mary (Maree), in San Francisco, California, and went to work briefly for the Federal Housing Administration.
In late 1945 he purchased Menlo Textiles, a national purveyor of custom-loomed fabrics in Menlo Park, California, some thirty miles south of San Francisco. He and Mary moved to Menlo Park, where he operated the weaving company for the next l8 years. He was drawn to it, as he told a local newspaper, " because it was a creative enterprise-something I could do with my hands." Belangie's artistic streak extended to fabric designs as well as pen and ink landscape sketches.
During his tenure at Menlo Textiles and his sideline enterprise of selling real estate, he frequently had a reason to call into Menlo City Hall, and he began to volunteer for various committees. Soon, Belangie was appointed to the Menlo Regional Planning Committee Executive Council, the City and County Parks Committee, and the Master Plan Revisions Committee. He also became a member of the Menlo Historical Society, was an early advocate of the Menlo Public Library, and was instrumental in forming Menlo Park's Arts Commission.
His public service efforts led him to run for the Menlo Park City Council in 1950, an election that he won. He also became Mayor in 1954-55. In 1955, he resigned his Council seat owing to the press of business, but he was persuaded to join the Council again in 1957, when he was appointed to fill the vacancy left by the death of a councilman. Belangie remained a Councilman, being elected over and over again until l971, when he again resigned, this time to become Executive Vice President of the Menlo Park Chamber of Commerce.
Belangie had a simple formula for public service: "With my fellow councilmen, I felt our first job, as representatives of the people, was to be responsible, and responsive, to furthering the amenities for living, working, and leisure." On the City Council he helped to design Menlo Park's innovative professional-administrative zoning policies, which enabled the city to expand commercial areas without eroding the city's basic residential character, policies that have been emulated by cities all over America. Another major contribution was his work to keep Stanford Research Institute (now SRI International) in Menlo Park.
A lifelong golfer, Belangie also assisted in the design and planning of the Menlo Park Sharon Heights Golf and Country Club, and served a term as the Club's Executive Secretary and General Manager.
But what he is remembered most fondly for is "the Fountain." The Fountain, a replica of a fountain in Rome called "Neptune's Family," had been cast in the 1860s to grace the grounds of Thurlow Lodge in Menlo Park, the home of W. E. Barron. It survived a destructive fire in 1872, when the home was owned by Milton Latham. Later, the property, including the mansion, gatehouse, and fountain, were purchased by Timothy Hopkins, nephew of Mark Hopkins. When Menlo Park moved its Administrative Complex onto this land in the late 1960s, two relics of its former grandeur remained: the gatehouse, and the broken and rusty fountain, greatly in need of restoration.
The gatehouse was restored without much fuss, but Neptune's Family remained in ruins. Belangie, struck by its beauty, vowed to save it from the breakers and see it restored, and for a number of years it sat forlornly in his backyard. Finally, his efforts to persuade the City that the Fountain's historic value was such that the metal sculpture should be restored were successful. The sparkling fountain, with its plumbing repaired, and basking in a new coat of paint, was placed beneath an old oak tree near the gatehouse, and is still burbling away today (2000).
Mike Belangie, however, did not live to see the Fountain restored. He died in 1974 at the age of 69. But ten years later, the Fountain's restoration was completed by the City, and in a ceremony held on July 4, 1984, its restoration was celebrated, with a plaque placed at the base of Neptune's Family, dedicating it to Mike Belangie.
Scope and Content
The Michael Louis (and Mary) Belangie Collection is extensive (9 linear feet). It is divided as follows: Boxes 1, 2, 8 (oversize), and 9 (oversize photo album) contain files pertaining principally to Belangie's personal life. Boxes 3 through 7 contain principally material that, although about the Belangies, represents "life as it was " in Menlo Park, California, 1945-1980. These files contain such material as costs of operating a household, automotive records and costs, appliance and other advertisements, insurance records, stock transactions and investments, medical records and costs, and yearly income taxes.
Collection Contents
- Series 1. Personal files
  - Subseries 1. Michael L. Belangie
    - Birth certificate (2 copies, 1 clip) See also box 8, folder 11941, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Diploma, Butte High School5/29/1921 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Personal data (army discharge, resumes, notification of death, etc.)1945-1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Wallet & i.d. cards1936-1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Selective service correspondence, army discharge942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - War experience (letter, 4 clips, telegram)1942, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - USDA (2 clips)1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - As Menlo Park City Councilman (correspondence, clips, certificate of election) See also box 8, folder 31952-1974 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Chamber of Commerce (correspondence, clips, membership roster) See also box 8, folder 5 1949-1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - The Town Club (correspondence, membership rosters, newsletters)1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "The Fountain" (correspondence, publicity, clips) See also box 8, folder 81978-1984 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Personal correspondence1946-1974 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - USDA correspondence1942-1946 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence to/from relatives1952-1984 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Business correspondence1953-1973 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Gratitude & congratulatory correspondence1938-1961 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Souvenir menu, UALFeb. 1950 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - "Train Collectors Quarterly"Apr. 1954 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Kistler coat of armsnd (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Disability claim & correspondence1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Legal matters1975 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - "Little House" Menlo Senior Center1954 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Loan application1957 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Assets1974 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Final illness medical statements1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Death certificate, correspondence, obituaries1974 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Subseries 2. Mary Belangie
    - Civil service records1946-1964 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Correspondence1943-1983 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Will (copy)1957 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Drivers license, driving certificate, ticket1950, 1980s (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Palo Alto Women's Club1969 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Recipesnd (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Directions to peoples' housesnd (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Sears charge accountnd (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Transfer of Oldsmobile to brother1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Miscellaneous notesnd (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Series 2. Menlo Textiles
  - Menlo Textiles brochure1960 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Menlo Textiles partnership agreement, bank acct1947-1960 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Photos (9)[1950s?] (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - 35 mm slides1950s (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Publicity 1951 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Income tax returns1948, 1956-60 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Sale of corporation1961 ff (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Series 3. Subject files
  - Subseries 1. Belangie family subject files
    - Appliance warranties & instructions1960s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Automobile insurance and loan1955-1980 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Automotive maintenance1960s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Calif. Senior citizen property tax assistance1972-1980 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Calif. Water Service statements1967-1974 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Personal health (news clips)1970s (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - DMV registration, handbooks, test, etc1950s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - House improvements & techniques1950s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Real estate matters1960s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - School facilities, reading list1940 & 1972 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Miscellaneous pamphlets1948-1955 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Medicare brochures[1960s-1970s] (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Medicare benefits claims & notes1970s (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Subseries 2. Sharon Heights subject files
    - Sharon Heights Golf & Country Club bylaws, etc.1961, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Sharon Heights Golf & Country Club, steering committee & board of directors meetings1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Sharon Heights Golf & Country Club, general manager records1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Sharon Heights Magazine "Duffer" & brochures1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Golf instruction clippings1970s (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Subseries 3. Menlo Park & vicinity subject files
    - "San Mateo County, its Story"1967 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - "Trees of Menlo Park"1972 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - "Menlo Park Centennial, 1874-1974" See also box 8, folder 171974 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - "Menlough Park"1970s (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - "Menlo Park Today"1966 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - "Menlo Park Today"1967 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - "Menlo Park Today"1968 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - "Menlo Park Today"1969 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "Menlo Park Today"1970 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "Menlo Park Today"1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - "Menlo Park Today"1971 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - "Menlo Park Today"1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - "Menlo Park Today"1976 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - "Menlo Park Comprehensive Plan, 2000" See also box 8, folders 19 and 231974 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - "Menlo Park Comprehensive Plan, 2000"1974 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Menlo Park official government stationery1970s (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - "Oak Meadows of Atherton"1976 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - "Atherton Lands"1979 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Series 4. Miscellaneous books
  - "Artisans & Technicians" (in French)[1960?] (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - AAA "Southwestern Tour Book"1964 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - "1001 New Decorating Ideas"[1950?] (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Series 5. Personal finance files
  - Investing (clippings)1960s (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Investment records1955-1983 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Investment records1982-1986 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Stock dividends (notes)1959-1982 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Stock transactions, AVCO1960-1980 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Stock transactions, U.S. Steel1950-1960 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Stock transactions, Host International1966-1982 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Stock transactions, Itek, Camelot1967-1983 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Stock transactions, Mitchum, Jones & Templeton1962-1973 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Stock transactions, Tenneco1963, 1970s (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Stock transactions, Lundborg1953-1970 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Stock transactions, Capital Preservation1981-1983 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Stock transactions, Morgan Stanley1958-1978 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Stock transactions, Dean Witter1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Stock transactions, Miscellaneous1946, 1970s (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Bank statements, Bank of America1982-1984 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Bank statements, Wells Fargo1978-1987 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Bank statements, Wells Fargo (cont'd)1978-1987 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Bank statements, First Interstate1985-1988 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Bank statements, Great Western1984-1988 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Pass books, Wells Fargo1944-1968 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Pass books, Northern Cal., UCB, BofA1944-1980 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Check registers, Wells Fargo1951-1972 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Check registers, various1955-1987 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Taxes, news clippingsnd (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Tax information1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Income tax returns & receipts1939-1947 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Income tax returns & receipts1945-1951 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Income tax returns & receipts1955 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Income tax returns & receipts1956 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Income tax returns & receipts1958 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Income tax returns & receipts1959 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Income tax returns & receipts1961 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Income tax returns & receipts1962 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Income tax returns & receipts1963 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Income tax returns & receipts1964 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Income tax returns & receipts1965 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Income tax returns & receipts1966 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Income tax returns & receipts1967 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Income tax returns & receipts1968 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Income tax returns & receipts1969 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Income tax returns & receipts1970 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Income tax returns & receipts1971 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Income tax returns & receipts1972 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Income tax returns & receipts1973 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Income tax returns & receipts1974 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Income tax returns & receipts1975 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Income tax returns & receipts1976 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Income tax returns & receipts1977 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Income tax returns & receipts1978 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Income tax returns & receipts1979 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Income tax returns & receipts1980 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Income tax returns & receipts1981 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Income tax returns & receipts1982 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Income tax returns & receipts1983 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Income tax returns & receipts1984 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Income tax returns & receipts1985 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Income tax returns & receipts1986 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Income tax returns & receipts1987 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Income tax returns & receipts1988 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Income tax returns & receipts1989 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Income tax returns & receipts1990 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Income tax returns & receipts1992 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Income tax returns & receipts1993 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Income tax returns & receipts1995 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - San Mateo County taxes1965-1992 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Series 6. Insurance files
  - Veterans' Benefits1951-1974 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Medical records1939, 1961-69 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Medical records1972-1976 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Medical records1977-1985 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Menlo Clinic Medical Reports1964-1988 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Aetna Insurance (Chamber of Commerce)1971 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Medical insurance, Bay Pacific1987 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Medical insurance, Blue Shield1946-1974 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Medical insurance, Blue Shield1946-1974 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Medical insurance, Blue Shield1975-1985 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Medical insurance, Kaiser1985 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Medical insurance, Insurance Company of America1958-1972 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Life insurance, Prudential1938-1964 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Life insurance, Metropolitan (M.L. Belangie)1944-1974 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Life insurance, (Mary Belangie)1938-1976 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Life insurance, Veterans Administration1951-1974 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Accident insurance (Menlo Park City)1970 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Homeowners' insurance1957-1988 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Automobile insurance1957-1988 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Personal property insurance1967-1987 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Series 7. Magazines (some include Menlo Textiles advertising)
  - Architectural Digest, December1979 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Architectural Digest, March 1980 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Architectural Digest, Mar/Apr1985 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Architectural Digest, Vol XII, # 1nd (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Architectural Digest, Vol XII, # 2nd (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Architectural Digest, Vol XIII, # 2nd (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Architectural Digest, Vol. XIII, # 3nd (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Architectural Digest, Vol ?nd (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - House & Garden, April1949 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - America's Fabrics. MacMillan, NY1947 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Shaping America's Products. Reinhold Pub.Corp., NY1956 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - haping America's Products. Reinhold Pub.Corp., NY. Duplicate copy (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Series 8. Oversize materials
  - Subseries 1. Miscellaneous
    - M.L. Belangie, birth cert., marriage license1935, 1941 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - M.L. Belangie, publicity photos (22 & 1 clipping)1913-[1970?] (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - M.L. Belangie, Menlo Park City Councilman (2 clips). See also box 1, folder 81962, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 2. Clippings
    - George Liddle (Willow Expressway)1971 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - M.L. Belangie, Chamber of Commerce1971 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - M.L. Belangie as artist1976 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - "I stole my greatest story,"1958 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Belangie & "The Fountain" See also box 1, folder 111984 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Sharon Heights Golf & Country Club. See also box 1, folders 57-601950s-1960s (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Golden Acorn Awards, Menlo Park1970s (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Menlo Park Civic Center1970 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Fountain, Lindenwood, Flood Estatend (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Menlo Park, Sherwood Hall, Hopkins Estatend (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Menlo Park City government1960s (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Alza Company1970 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Medicare & Social Security1960-1970 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Menlo Park Centennial. See also box 2, folder 31974 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Subseries 3. Maps
    - San Francisco1973 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Menlo Park, general plan1966 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Menlo Park1973-1974 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Menlo Parknd (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Menlo Park1988 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Menlo Park, "Toward 2000". See also box 2, folders 14 & 151974 (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - "How to find a library": news article1971 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Subseries 4. Scrapbook
    - Oversize scrapbook/photo album1930s-1974 (Box 9)